Okay. Good morning, everyone. And
welcome to iCleared,
2026.
We're very excited to have have you here
in in in in
in Rio. We have a
great program for you. Before
we get started though, there's a couple of notes about
safety. I think everyone
everyone can have have a great time. But everyone
should be aware of your surroundings at all times.
And a lot of this is is very common sense stuff. You know,
don't get don't get distracted
by your phone. Don't get
into a un unmarked car
and just be be be be be be be be we we we
aware of a very thing going on. Going
around you. If you
do get into to trouble, there's emergency
phone numbers here. For for
the police and and and and so on
that that you can that you that you you
can call.
New this year, we have a new map online.
You can go to iiiclrmap.com.
And this will show you where you are.
In relation to everything going on here.
We are in
we are in the red theater
here. And if you're not
on the WiFi yet, the, WiFi WiFi
code is,
I I clear 26 and the password is Conference.
Okay. So with that, I'm gonna hand it off to Barrows to
talk about the the program.
Alright. Hello everyone. Welcome to ICLAR.
We have an exciting setup
of keynote speakers. Starting
with Maya, who's going to give a talk immediately after
this. Maxwelling today
afternoon. And Percy,
Katie, Karen, and Pablo.
You can look at, if
if you're here, you've probably downloaded the iClare
app. If you go to the schedule, it will tell
you when the keynotes are.
The actual blog post also announces the
titles in the abstracts for these keynotes.
One
one,
note, Percy is having
some travel troubles.
So his keynote might be rescheduled
We will, send an email out to all attendees.
Once the details are finalized.
So, just to,
give you, an overview of this
iClare, we have, as I mentioned, six
keynote speakers. We
have two test of time awards, two
outstanding paper award winners, and one
honorable mention. This year, we
had 19,000, roughly
19,000 papers submitted. Out
of which about 5,300
were accepted. For an acceptance
rate of 27%.
Of these accepted papers,
224 are oral
presentations, They are spread
over six sessions,
in six parallel tracks. So you
can look at the schedule to figure out which
track or on and which sessions you want to
attend. In addition,
to these papers and posters and URLs,
are also 21 in person socials,
and 40 workshops. Again, you can look at the
schedule, and it will tell you when these are,
when and where these are. So this
is sort of a rough overview of
the schedule. We have
sort of keynotes and mornings
and afternoons and oral sessions in between. The poster
sessions note that the poster sessions overlap
with the oral sessions. But they go a
bit longer.
So after the orals, you can look at look through the posters
as well if you want to do both.
So Okay. So, this
is probably the moment many of you are waiting
for. We let
me quickly announce the awards. We'll
have a more detailed ceremony in the
evening when we'll announce sort
of the the process, in more detail.
So let's go to awards.
We have two outstanding paper
awards year. The first one is
transformers are inherently succinct.
The second one is LLMs get
lost in multi turn conversation.
Congratulations to all the winner to to both
the winners.
We also have an outstanding paper, honorable
mention This is the Polar Express
optimal matrix sign methods, and their
applications to the muon algorithm.
And this year, we have two test
of time awards. These are papers
that were presented at ICLER twenty sixteen
and are being awarded for their impact in the field.
The first is unsupervised
representation learning, with deep convolutional
generative adversarial networks.
And the second is continuous control
with deep reinforcement learning.
So
So the two Test of Time award
winners will have, talks
tomorrow at 05:45PM
and 06:15PM.
I'd also like to thank, all
our mentors for, offering office
hours and mentoring. They
are in two time slots in each of the three
days. So you can go to the 12PM slot
or the 01:15PM slot.
The rooms are 206, 209,
and 212. Walk ins
are welcome, so if you've not signed up, you can easily
go.
So that's it in terms of opening remarks.
We'll see you at the opening ceremony
today evening for, more detailed
presentation. And local entertainment.
And now, I'll hand over to
Sandra to introduce our first keynote
speaker,
Hello, everybody, and
thank you for coming. It's the first
session. And I'm super excited to
introduce Maya,
Maya Materich is a chaired and
distinguished professor of computer
science with the appointments in
neuroscience and pediatrics at University
of Southern California.
She's also a principal scientist
in Google DeepMind. The
she received her PhD and master thesis
in computer science and
AI from MIT.
And she is a member of National Academy
of Engineering. American
Academy of Arts and Sciences,
fellow in pretty much every organization that
can be and received numerous
awards including Presidential Award for
Excellence in Science Mathematics
and engineering mentoring from
president Obama.
The and many others.
She is a pioneer in the field
of socially assistive robotics,
and her research is in developing human machine
interaction methods for personalized support
for user with challenges such as autism,
Alzheimer's disease and so on.
Her research group had conducted
the largest and many of the first
field studies in very challenging and complex environments
such as hospitals, nursing homes,
and so on. The
to produce the deep insights.
Beyond that, Maya is a dear friend
collaborator, and my mentor for
years. Who's kind of thinking about
AI in society and societal impact has
really shaped my thinking about
the domain. So I'm hoping that
this talk shapes a bit of yours. Thank you.
Good morning, everyone.
Now you know how I got this talk. It's all
about who you know. So get
connected. Speaking of being
connected, I'm waiting. To
be connected. So I
wanna thank you for being here.
This early for many of you. I know some of you, maybe it's not
as big a jet lag, but for some of us, it's
a lot. Thank you for
those who didn't get registered because of the power
failure so you could be here also. I'm
excited.
I may have to mind the talk. It's gonna
be great.
It was connected early. Thank you. Thank you very
much.
You may have to get your phones out and and turn
the lights on and do the wave
a little bit and just kind of get us in the
mood Maybe that's missing.
I love this venue.
I'm gonna start opening in stadiums soon.
So please wait for that.
Night It was working.
It was working before.
Is it different? Do you have to plug in? Here?
Is it
we can try it.
I will be expecting more applause than
that. Thank
you. Thank you. Thank
Thank you. May you all have
great this this
Alright. I'm gonna talk about a lot of things.
And I just wanna tell you that because we're already starting
late, I will not end early. And,
but I want to encourage you to ask me all
questions you want. If there's no time at the end,
catch me. I'm here. Especially
right after the talk. If you can't catch me, I promise.
My promise is I'm here and I will
answer every question that you have.
It's my commitment. Alright. Let's go.
So AI.
This is it. We're in it. We're
in the era of AI. Here's
you. You're right there. You're working in AI. If you're
here, you're working in AI. You're right there dotting
the I of AI. So
why? Why are you
working in AI?
Why? Everyone working in AI?
Why do we do this thing? Well,
many of us are doing it because of the intellectual
curiosity what is possible. It's
an amazing frontier For some of us, we've
been here for decades literally
and now there's a breakthrough Things have
opened up. The discovery is the
energy is amazing. Or,
you know, maybe monetizing amazing possibilities
for various products.
Some people will say that we're only really doing it
for safety because if we don't do it, other
people will do it. It's the why we have to do it. There's
kind of a race going on if you haven't noticed, right?
And then there's the greater good. Maybe
just maybe, we can finally use AI
for human centered technologies.
And benefits. And we
like to think that there's kind of a a nice flywheel
that's bringing these together. Maybe.
Right? What I
would really just encourage you to think
about is is that really happening? Or
because? Motivations
are often mixed and incentives
are often contradictory. So
I want to challenge you. I love a big audience. So when
I have a big audience, I like to challenge
you on why you're doing what you're doing.
Really think about it. And when it comes to AI,
wow, what amazing potential and
impact we are already having and
can have. So think about it. You're
making a choice. You're hereby choice.
You're making a choice in what you're doing. Think about it
hard. Think about
it. So why are you doing it? I'll talk
a little bit about, why I, and I
really mean we, my
group, mostly at USC,
I will also talk about Google DeepMind work.
Is working in AI. So why?
So ideally, this is
the axis. Is intellectual curiosity, but
it is very much driven by real world
tech we're developing. So
we want to use specifically human machine
interaction to better understand humans.
So to understand human behavior, we can
run human subject studies
or we can do human machine interactions
studies and really titrate and control
what we're studying. That's a really interesting method
that's becoming ever more powerful with
AI. But just remember to keep the human in the loop.
Because if you're trying to understand humans by
simulating humans, not having
any humans in the loop, you're probably not studying
humans anymore. The
other part is as we do that, we
really are very use inspired. So I'm I'm super
pragmatic personally. Since I had kids,
I became all about how is this going to impact
their lives? As opposed to
just the intellectual curiosity, which is awesome in
itself but as you get older, you
might become like you might start
to think more broadly. So let's
talk about intelligence first of all because you know,
the I and the AI human
intelligence evolved over a very
long time in the context of a specific
body In every case, there is
a body. And that body is in an
environment. There is no intelligence.
Without the body and the environment.
So many people will argue this today because we
have intelligence without a body.
But just how intelligent
can that intelligence be it isn't
embodied and situated? And so,
it turns out that there are aspects of human
intelligence that drove the evolution
of intelligence. We're still missing in AI.
Great opportunities. So we're missing in particular
the embodied part. It's being
worked on very heavily. Right? People are aware
of Bill and billions and billions of dollars of
investment in robotics. And
in particular in humanoid robotics.
Which is interesting. It's a bit of a narrow
focus. It is being developed. So we
understand that the physical embodiment is
important. What we don't seem to understand
as a field overall is that the social
and the socio emotional part
is completely missing. And guess what?
This is what drove human
intelligence. We all of us are
as intelligent as we are. Because of the complexity
of the social structures that we interact with
and because of the emotional
underpinning that drives us as
animals fundamentally.
To deal with the world around us and in particular
others like us. This is really
necessary. So you know the physical, the
cognitive, and the socio emotional.
And, you know, AI isn't doing that. So when we
think about AGI, right, we're gonna
get to the artificial general intelligence. Well, how
general can it be if it
isn't really situated in a
complex environment and within a
body to which the to relate the world.
And so there's an argument by a large part of
the field or some part
of the field, growing part of the field. That you
need for AGI to do the to
address the embodiment and the socio emotional
grounding. And in fact, you might
argue that that's the best way to get more data.
Because right now, as we're teleopting
humanoids to do things,
and doing a lot of sim.
And a little bit of sim to real, what
we're not doing is having comp
collecting data. And that's what
we need. Because
in old AI, there is this symbol to signal,
like how do you connect high level
reasoning to real world data? Well,
now, how do you connect all
of the things that models are doing to the real environment
and to other people and to other agents. So
that's still missing. And I think people
are starting to get to it, but people
just figured out like a year ago that we're
missing stars. Data. In robotics.
Well, you know. A roboticist for decades,
I could have told you that. So
there we have a ways to go. Before we
hit upon true AGI. But
know. We're apparently going there.
And so now the question becomes, okay,
so someday we'll get there. We can have a lot of futuristic
arguments as to when that is. Is it in two years,
three years, fifty years, twenty years? Whatever.
That's it'll happen when
it happens. But then what?
And they're going to be a
lot of interesting social
implications and, you know, just most recently
you've seen there's been even some violence
in response to AI and
you know, people are responding
to what they're hearing and they're hearing in
And so the question is, how do you design
systems that
the world will accept and find beneficial?
Because there's really really no simple
answer, and it's good to not be naive. It's
good to remember that while you believe
in the technology, does not mean that the
person outside of this door does.
And so I'm in robotics,
historically. And there's been a lot of
work over the last twenty five years on
putting robots with people These were
research robots. Right? And just seeing what happens.
And it's really interesting because this
interesting bifurcation happens.
That people relate to machines
the machines are well designed, and
non threatening, and that it's not a high
stakes environment. People relate to
machines a lot of times like they relate to
people. They feel empathy, they feel relatedness,
they want to help,
or they might find that it's
creepy they have cognitive dissonance, and
people often bully and abuse robots.
There are a lot of videos that get taken down
because of what people are doing to robots even in
public. So the robots and
the machines in our world, and we see this in
in terms of even the searches that people do.
With agents and models. They can bring
out the best in people or they can bring out the worst in
people. Just the same as people
do. Because they're like us, but not
quite like us. So they evoke this
in group, out group identity
behavior. And that's really complex
because that too can be manipulated.
So, what do you do given that landscape?
So, the stuff that we have done is
this human centered AI that I like to believe
is for the greater good. Because at least
the it taps into this massive
need around supporting human
health education and training.
But, I'm gonna argue, and I always argue, I
love this little bit, I show it in every slide,
we need balance. So if you look at
the vast majority of technologies being
created today, they are about replacement
rather than augmentation. Not exclusively,
but largely. And so,
I just encourage you to think about what are you doing?
And what are the implications of what you're doing? Oh, it's
so easy to just focus on the next conference public.
But think about the implications. Is
what you're creating aimed at entirely
replacing a human's role in something?
What is that role? I mean, literally, unless
they're taking nuclear cores out of something,
do you really wanna replace them and where are they going?
And why is that now your problem? So,
thinking about this balance between
automation and replacement versus augmentation,
and enhancement of human ability.
I just encourage you to do that.
And so, the for the work that we have done for the last,
gosh, twenty five years, I'm old.
Has been about augmentation. So that's what the focus
will be.
Alright. Now, let's talk about us humans.
Turns out we are a mess.
We are just a mess.
Remember, this research is going to be about human behavior,
helping people do good things for themselves.
Well, it turns out we're really bad at
doing things that are good for ourselves.
We know what we should do. But we don't do it.
And it's not because we're just weak
That's a really uninformed
shallow opinion. Turns out it's really
really hard because everything around us
in many ways conspires by
design to make that harder.
So human health is really hard.
No matter where you are. So,
what do we do with that? So, again, twenty
five years ago, we developed this field of
socially robotics and the idea is that
the machine is there help you
help yourself. So notice the indirection.
The machine is not helping you,
to do something. It's helping you do something
yourself. It's not doing it for you.
So, it's not replacement. It's not
taking some other human out of your life. It's making you
do it. It's helping you do it.
So there's a lot of work
in HCI, in AI,
subsequently ML, on perception
and monitoring and understanding what people are
doing. And then giving you data.
And telling you what to do.
That's the top. Square up
there. Rectangle. Turns out that's
insufficient. So the quantified
self, you knowing a lot about yourself
in which there's a huge amount of research right now.
Right? Like models will tell you anything you wanna
know. Great. Guess what?
It doesn't matter. Because
the vast majority of humanity
will not change its behavior based on just
information. Information does
not drive behavior. Motivation
drives behavior. And
changing human motivation
is really, really hard. So, we're interested
in this socio emotional
stuff. How do we provide companionship
that is supportive for people so they can
have the motivation to do what's good for them?
It's a really interesting in direction. And
this field is old. So there's an article from
Jerome, in the New
Yorker from o nine talking about the
field. So, the field started in the early aughts and there
was an early article. I think it's always fun to go back to
it and see what they wrote and
where we are now. Okay. What does
a socially assistive robot do? What can
it what does it perseve
so first of all, it needs to have real time
vision. You wanna understand the user in real time. These
are real time interactions in the real world.
Situated, embodied. Right? So you gotta understand the user.
And you wanna understand the user not just like what's
my pose, but like what's my affect?
What is my likely intent? In
the context of this interaction?
What is my gesture? What is my activity?
It's a lot of work on this in the past. It's greatly
powered by models now. Also speech
in particular, it's with speech to speech models.
Now. Right? We prefer that people talk rather
than they write. It depends on the interaction.
And so, there's a lot of personalization that already happens
in this because it turns out, as I'll say a little bit longer,
in a bit, general
models are terrible at this. So I'm sorry,
but current foundation models are terrible at,
for example, personalized affect recognition.
Guess what? It will not recognize whether
you're smiling or frowning very effectively.
So that's still a hard problem. So there are
a lot of specialized deep models that are used
for this in real time pre trained,
rather than using a foundation model.
Then there's always dialogue. Right? Generally,
machine people. Great.
That if there's one problem that is
largely I won't say solved, but
almost there, great.
You do need to prompt them or
fine tune them or both with domain
specific knowledge to make sure that they're staying
within the rails. For example, I'll tell you later
work with cognitive behavioral therapy with
robot You really don't want
the model to go off and suggest
things it thinks it's best.
Then of course there's the physically embodied behavior. Let's not
forget that. These are actual robots.
Why does that matter? I'll show you a slew of
results of why it actually matters that it'd be
a physically embodied robot as opposed
to a chatbot. So, if it's
a physically embodied robot, then of
course, how does it move? Turns out it's important.
You can't just sit there and then occasionally
move and freak you out. It's gotta move
in a way that is context relevant.
And not distracting and
And then it likely has a body that isn't actually
humanoid as we'll talk about, Then,
how do you know what the right behavior is for a non humanoid,
non biologically like body?
So, and then finally, there's
adaptation. Every person is different. Every
person is changing and adapting. Hopefully, you're
teaching them something. They're learning something anytime a
human interacts with a
model or an AI system. The human is
changing in real time. We're always
learning. We're always adapting. So the system has to
do the same. So usually, there's an RL
component that's also adapting. So
all this is going on all at once in these systems.
It's a lot.
So, wow. What are the robots?
Has anyone heard of humanoid robots over
here? Anyone? Anyone? Yeah.
Maybe? A few people? Uh-huh. So
massive billions of dollars, billions
and billions and billions are going into
humanoids. Guess what
small surprise secret for you, People
don't want humanoids in their lives. Yes.
There are some people, a very small number of
people who are very pro tech
ready and have the disposable income to
currently rent humanoids so that they would collect data out
of their homes. For free.
You pay $500 a month to give
your data away for free to a
company. That's the thing, but how many people want
to do that? So not a lot. It turns out
currently, humanoids are certainly the hardest thing
to control and it's good that we're investing in
understanding that problem. It's we want to advance
robotics. But, if you think about the consumer
world, if you think about what do people want in
their homes, it will turn out
not to be humanoids first.
You can call me on it later. So,
we in research want to do really large studies.
We do studies with like a 120
So So, please, tell me where I can get
humanoids that work and are affordable to do
a study like that and then tell me where I
can get that many participants willing to put a humanoid
in their life.
So, we're very interested in scaling things
up and that's why we've developed really
very very low cost. This is sub $300
Super relatable, flexible,
scalable robots. And they do all the things that you saw
in the previous slide, but they don't have the
bodies that are
potentially dangerous and highly expensive.
And they're also acceptable to pretty much every
participant we worked with. From the elderly
with Alzheimer's to children
with autism, to college students with,
anxiety and depression.
But why do we need a robot? Can't we just
use an app? I mean, come on. This
robot is not so complicated. Does it matter?
Well, it turns out it does. So now we've got
over fifty years of neuroscience studies to show
that even the simplest of embodiments
is processed differently by your brain,
than a screen. Tons
and tons of data. Literally, your brain is engaged
differently different
regions and different levels of activation.
We can go into great detail on this Their
papers we can chat. I also
got tired of answering this question of like, well,
but can't you do it in simulation? So,
we did a meta review back
in 2019. Woah. That seems like a long time
ago. That's the argument would be even stronger now.
But we looked at all of the HCI
versus HRI studies? Human
computer interaction versus human robot interaction,
all of the comparisons that had been done it was
quite a lot actually.
And just showed that there's a huge amount
of data backing the fact that when you're physically
co present, and having an interaction,
you are more engaged. That's really important
because if you're not engaged, nothing is happening. Right?
So engagement is higher. You enjoy
it more, things we enjoy we remember better,
three, you learn more and four, you retain whatever
it is that you experienced and learned much
longer. So, whether you're trying
to entertain people or you're trying to educate them
you're trying to help them recover, these are the outcomes
you want. They're much stronger in
physically co present embodied interactions
than they are through screens. Not a surprise.
It's just how our brains have evolved. But
people still need to sometimes be reminded why
no, there is no app for that.
So, now wanna show you a bunch of studies
quickly to just kind of entertain you with some
of the work we've done. Here's an example
of something that you absolutely cannot do
with a screen ever. Can't do it.
Okay. We were interested in working
with really young children
we can now turn off the audio. But I
just wanted you to hear some baby sounds.
Okay. So, we were interested in
helping very, very young babies
to develop the use of their muscles because
they were at risk for developmental delays.
You can you can based on sibling
outcomes tell that maybe some child is going
to have trouble as they develop. But you cannot
determine that really early on, like, maybe
he's just flail and you can't necessarily predict
if that flailing is typical or not up until the
point That's called motor babbling. Up until a
certain point where you notice, oh, they're not catching up.
With the developmental milestones.
By the time they're missing the milestones, it's too late.
So, you wanna predict it and catch it. And
then you want to intervene. So, if you wanna
intervene, remember I'm all about intervention,
how do you help the situation?
How do you get a baby to quit kick
his leg higher? Okay. How would you do
it? I'm gonna ask you. You're not parents, most of you. You
have no idea. Simple answer,
you can't. You can't tell a baby,
hey, kick your leg up but a little higher.
Now, they don't understand. Not
paying attention. Okay.
If you show them, do you think they're gonna imitate?
No. You're way too big. As an adult, they're
gonna look at your face. So babies are at
that developmental stage looking at your face. They're not looking
at your body. They don't even know to look at where you're
pointing yet. But,
it turns out because we are loaded
with mira neuro
imitate what we see. We're just inhibited
usually, so we're not imitating in real time, but
as I do this, a part of your brain is ready to imitate
this. But you're inhibited. If you
have a certain deficit, you will actually do it
in real time, but no one seems to. Okay.
So, babies,
are able to imitate certain things,
but that those things are basically the size and
shape of a baby. So if you could get a baby
to show another baby that they should kick their leg up,
then that would work. But mean, I'm
back to my first problem. How to get a baby to do something?
So how do I get a coach baby to coach the other
baby? Can't be done. But, you could get a
robot the size and shape of a baby to be
the baby coach. So we did exactly
that. We used the now robots, which are not the shape
of a baby, but they're kind of roughly the size and
roughly the kinematics. And
lo and behold, just a tiny
bit of additional reinforcement, this is the other thing you
have to understand about babies, It's not enough just to
observe. They need a reward. So, the reward
was that bell that when they kick the
the ball, then they
get the bell. So, there It's a little pavlovian
that's what you have to do at the early developmental
stages. And so, we basically got a
robot to show the baby what to do. We use
some, deep models of attention
by Laurenti T and Pierre Baldy
from like ages ago would predict where
the baby would look What's the most salient? Because
by the way, you also can't just show babies things and expect
them to pay attention. You have to really pull
their attention. So we predicted
what would be most salient to them, we show them that,
have them look at the leg. And then they imitate
it. So, we were basically using a
robot to puppeteer a
baby. That is so
clever. And by the way, it was my students' work.
It wasn't mine. That is so clever.
And you can't do it any other way because by the way, you can
show babies videos of a bunch of stuff
and their, visual cortex is lighting up
like crazy. But there's no connection
with the mirror neurons and and with imitation.
It's too early. So it's
a beautiful example of where embodiment is
so fundamental and you often see this embodiment
in development. Which is why,
for example, you can't learn to move if you
don't do it early enough. So the the
the core role of embodiment is really obvious early
in development which is why it's interesting to do
this intervention. So, what's
the best embodiment? What's the right embodiment?
Again, I get asked this question. There's no such thing.
It's definitely not humanoids. Oh,
sorry. Every embodiment
has a role. Right? It's in context of a
task. So, did
a bunch of work, on trying to understand
people's expectations around embodiment.
And it turns out we have these inherent metaphors
in our heads like when we see something that's
animal like, we expect it to have animal like capabilities.
I've talked to people who are developing robot
dogs and they were always surprised when
I told them that people will look at that thing and they'll expect
it to be as smart and as fun as a dog.
And people are always surprised by this. I'm like, but
it's a robot. It's like, no. To a person, it looks
like a dog. It be able to do everything a dog does
and and a little bit more. Now
guess what when it's a humanoid?
Just how much do you think will
expect from it? A whole lot.
So, it may not it'll be a huge disappointment which
is why we wanna go for in a lot
of research embodiment that
create fewer expectations.
Or different expectations, which is why we go for these more
abstract embodiment.
Because every expectation is a bias by definition.
And, so, if it's a humanoid, but it's dressed in a particular
way, turns out all kinds of interesting gender
biases come up, which you can manipulate in various
ways. Alright. So,
let's go from embodiment to persona. This is
where we get into stuff that's really quite modern.
But I'm gonna talk about doing it back in 2008.
So we were interested in personality.
For a long time. Why? You all have personalities.
It's true. Please do
not ever spend any time looking up the
Myers Briggs. It's a cult. I have to share
this. If you learn nothing today, the Myers Briggs is a
cult. Look it up on Wikipedia. Super fun.
Looking at this particular person's story who developed
this cult, which companies still use
and to really really bad outcomes. Wanna
know your personality? Use the big five.
Okay? So, there's a big five scientifically grounded
method. But, your personality is not
a thing. In the moment, it changes
constantly. It's just certain predispositions
that you have. And, these
predispositions do determine how we relate to
other people. And so this is why for
example, a lot of companies now that
control large models that we interact
with, are tuning those models to have certain
personas or personalities or tone or
style. In order to relate
to most people. That also I
think is kind of not the right way to go because
people are very different. There's no average personality.
But there is a set
of personality profiles most people prefer.
So, most people prefer kind
of open, extroverted,
conscientious personality.
Unsurprisingly. But most people are
not necessarily open conscientious,
and extroverted. So who
you get along with in the moment in a particular
context really varies. And so, we wanted
to create robots with personality back
in 2007,
to see if it would be if it would have
an effect how people interact with robots. We had stroke
patients, We wanted them to do boring
exercises. We thought if the robot has
a personality that matches the user's
personality, maybe they will exercise longer
because know from human relationships
that if your personality is similar to the
personality of the
Hello? Also, you know, all this stuff about opposites
attracting, Totally scientifically
untrue. The more similar
you are to the person that you're interacting with
or
Boom, you'll learn something. It's
a fact. Anybody who's been in a relationship for a
long time will tell you that
it's so great that one person is a slob
and the other one is neat. Is it
how great is that? No. It's not great.
It will grade on you.
So the personality matching is actually a very powerful
effect. Effect. So we we did this. We
said, what is the expression of personality
in a robot? So, personality is
expressed in a lot of what you say, but it's expressed
very powerfully in your behavior.
So, let's just take extroversion introversion.
Just that dimension. Okay? Along that dimension,
extroverts are going to move more
going to get closer to you
thus their their pitch of their voice is going to be
higher, on average, regardless
of gender. And they're
going to kind of basically just
be a little bit more in your face.
And that's all physical back channel.
That's so you can do that with robots. You
don't need even to worry about what it's
saying. Then you get into what it's saying
and obviously extroverted language is
we know the linguistic markers for extroversion.
So, with our robot, we didn't even use language.
It We just used back channel body.
Move. Body movement. And
we found a very strong effect.
That in like a twenty minute interaction with a
stroke patient, if you match the personality,
you get significantly longer
exercise. And people also
enjoy it more. And, this is interesting too
because if you ask extroverts, they will say, I like
that one. And that one is the extrovert.
If you ask introverts, they
don't necessarily tell you, oh, I like that one.
Is the introverted. They say, oh, I like them all the
same. But they perform much longer
with the introverted robot.
So, it's really interesting because people are
very bad at at
their behavior tells all.
So now, as I said, we're in an age
where people are developing personalities for
models no matter what the models are being used
for. And this is important, and
it's also powerful and it's important
to do right. So, at
Google DeepMind, a couple years ago, we
started maybe more a couple of years, three years ago, we
started work on understanding whether
there are latent personalities to existing
models. So is a model
inherently more extroverted? Is
it inherently more conscientious? Than the the
average? And then also, if you
wanted it to be a particular personality,
in a way that actually is
grounded and lasts. So,
as you saw from the papers that stood the test
of time and current award papers,
models still can't do multi turn
conversations. So what does it mean for a model to have a personality
if it loses it after two turns?
And so, we developed I'm
very proud of this work.
This is really, really fundamentally deep
way to prompt
a personality. It's
psychometrically valid, has all of these properties
that are written over there, I encourage anybody
who is trying to have an
agent or a model
have a personality to really look at this. Because
if you're just prompting a model, if you just say,
okay, now talk to me like an extrovert.
Sorry. That's just that's shallow,
it doesn't work. But there are proper ways
of doing it and this is a way.
And this has been used now extensively
to actually create agents that have more predictive
personality. In a sustained way in the context
of health
We also did some additional work to look at
whether models with personalities
behave the way people behave with different
personalities when doing conflict resolution.
This is interesting because it turns out
that again, people who are extroverts
and open tend to
be the best people to argue with.
Because they're open about what they want, and
the negotiation is usually
So, So, most people prefer to argue with
people like that. Even if they're not themselves
like that. So we did some exploration on
how models argue with each other and how
that how argue and negotiate.
And there's some really interesting, results that
come out of this. For example, that with people,
neuroticism, which is one of the dimensions of
of personality,
is a best predictor on the of
the final outcome. So, if you're if you're kind of
neurotic, that's gonna
drive your outcomes in in,
disputes. Take that personality
first. As
opposed to models, where for models,
different features, extraversion and and agreeableness
were actually much better at the determining
how the outcome would happen. So the models
were not really behaving like people, which is interesting.
At least today. So this was done like a
few months ago. And of course,
you know, the leading models. Claude
and Gemini, were most similar to human strategic
behavior. So just just as a that's a largely
a model size issue. If we had done this two
years ago, they wouldn't have been as good. But it's an interesting thing
when we think about these models. Right? They're
trained on a bunch of human data, but it doesn't
mean that they're representing actually
human behavior. So given that
personality is a huge driver of human behavior,
it's interesting to look at these disparities.
Once you have personality,
can start building personas. Right? And so we
did this ages ago with trying to get
kids to you know, getting robust personalities
to get kids to do things. More
recently, again, at GDM,
took those psychiatrically
that psychometrically
grounded profiles of personality developed
synthetic personas. And, these were
trained on some health data in
the health context or they might be trained
on demographic data. This creates really rich
personas. So again, this is really
important because a huge amount
of work on models today
is developing these personas that you use for evaluating.
So evaluating something or other. You're simulating
humans. You're simulating scenarios. You're simulating
this better or the other thing. How good your
simulation of persona is is really important.
So again, this was work at ACL
just last year. Wow, we've gone into
the future. This is twenty thousand
two zero five. That's when the paper
will come out. No, no. No, no,
the paper came out actually last year.
But it is about basically creating again
these grounded personas whose
behavior over time will be more predictable.
Really into the future, Like model
behavior over a long timelines.
Is an unsolved problem. But at least this has
a better time line.
Empathy is another human
behavior trait which predicts your behavioral
outcomes. Right? So, if you're empathetic towards someone,
it'll actually change your behavior. Is
important. For health behavior as well. It's
So lots of people have created
agents or robots that behave like they're
empathetic. It's not hard. Right? They'll just,
you know, any model will say, oh, I'm sorry you feel that
way. Is it sorry? Well, of course, it's
not really sorry, but it says that, makes you
feel good. Right? That's
that's not hard. It's not even interesting. The
part that's interesting is can a model
make you be empathetic?
Because if you are empathetic,
first, it's better for people around you,
it makes a better world. But
this is the better reason if you'd like, if you're selfish,
Empathy is correlated with better health.
So, if you're an empathetic person,
you're nice to other people, your health
is actually better. Isn't that
amazing considering how people are behaving these days?
With all the polarization? And then you're like, oh
my God, our health costs are like here.
We're all mean. And I wonder that
there's no connection between these two things. Well,
there is. So we were interested in
getting robots to be to
create empathy in people. And, it's very
interesting to see how you would do that
looked at kind of first person versus third person
storytelling, People relate
to humans better than they relate to robots.
Still today. May change.
People like stories when you're talking about yourself.
So, if you're a robot, you're talking about yourself.
Then the person feels more empathetic than if a robot
is talking about another robot. And
then more interestingly, how
helpless and vulnerable should the robot
or the agent be? This is
a huge question actually in politics.
Because saying I'm sorry
issuing an apology is seen as weakness.
How funny given that if the
agent or the robot is vulnerable,
people like it much better. And
people are much more forgiving.
So usually when I talk to people who are developing
robots, they talk about robots that behave perfect
and never get anything wrong and this will never happen.
They will get things wrong they will not be perfect.
But if they were acute and vulnerable, people
would accept that much better. So
we did a study where we had a robot constantly
fail So the robot, the person
is doing a task, the robot is supposed to help
them and and it's just failing
constantly. And so interestingly,
I was surprised actually because they're are
three kinds of robots. We looked at neutral robotic robots.
We looked at robots that were kind of funny robots
that were sad and pleading for help. And it was
the sad pleading robot that generated the most empathy
I found it annoying. Again, there's always
a distribution of human response.
But by far, people like the
sad pleading robot. But again, don't over generalize.
This was a study. In a real world
environment where you're like trying to catch a flight,
would you stop for the sad pleading robot?
Chances are no. Studies show that you won't
do that. So,
again, eliciting empathy, personality, lots
of stuff. Support groups, I'm gonna
skip that other than to now just flash
the highlights. We've
done studies where we've done robots as
supporting group
cancer survivors, anxiety, depression, etcetera.
Just having a robot in the room without
saying anything and just occasionally turning to
people to encourage them to talk
increases group cohesion. If you
have a human doing the same thing, it doesn't have that
effect. People relax
more around robots. That's interesting.
We also found that when we told people
that the robot was autonomous,
versus being remote controlled, Wizard
of Oz's, people said many more
personal things what they thought was an autonomous robot
than the robot that they thought was human controlled.
It turned out actually both robots were controlled through
an LLM that was being checked by a
human. But know, it's interesting it's
interesting how we behave very
differently based on what we believe.
And this will turn out to be important.
We would love love love to have robots understand
affect in real time. This is still
a really hard problem. So deep models
like open face, open smile, open pose,
they're still better than any foundation model.
Hello. You can't
no big model is as good as this. We just benchmarked
them and they're awful. And it has to do with the fact
that this is a really hard problem. So you think that you can
tell if I'm smiling or angry? You
really can't. You need context to get to
that high level feature. So, there are multiple
levels of features. There's like the low level features of where
my smile is, where my lips are, Well,
anything can detect that. But going
from that to understanding what my intent
is, that's much harder. Those are high level
features models are still bad at that big models.
And yet these smiles are so important.
In in my lab, we did work where we analyzed
three minute interactions between mothers
and infants And just from these three minute interactions
and the mother smiles, we could
tell one, the mental health state
of the mother
two, whether the child will a
year from then have developmental
delays. Eighty five percent
accuracy right now
at six months whether the child will have delays
based on the interaction they're having with mother
at six months. Incredibly powerful.
Yeah. We're trying to get the medical community to get
interested. Similarly, prosody.
Moms and bay and one year olds. These are not babies.
One moms and one year olds talking. One year old
So moms and one year old's moms
that interrupt the one year old's
often have really adverse early
life experiences themselves.
And if they interrupt
and they keep talking over the baby, that's very
predictive of their mental state as you
would imagine,
Similarly, if they if they interrupt and then don't
talk, very predictive of depression.
Also, is predictive of the child's outcomes
later on. These these subtleties
are incredibly important and by the way, the models are still
terrible at it. But then, deep models
are also great at some things like we
did some work a few years ago and by the way,
telling whether you're lying models are really
good at that. So, you sometimes can't
tell what's gonna be hard or easy. Engagement
is really hard. That's, you know, it's the billion
billion billion dollar question. How do
you engage and keep the engagement of a user?
We're interested in this from the health
perspective. Right? How do I get you to like do
exercise or, you know, pay attention to your
health, self regulate? Of course, the
entertainment industry is interested for other reasons.
Engagement is a tough problem,
We often study this in autism, because
it's very very difficult to
understand individuals who who have very atypical
affect atypical behaviors,
even within a session of twenty,
thirty minutes, much less
across a population. So it's kind of the
ultimate ML problem.
ML is not hard when you have a ton of data
and a reasonable distribution. It's
hard when you have sparse noisy data
and massive variance.
And that's what this population is
like. But by the way, that's what all behavioral challenges
are like. So whether you're looking at
mental health, anxiety, depression,
behavioral, anything related to behavior,
typically your data are going to be noisy,
relatively sparse for the specific
user. And there will be variance. Will
be very non stationary. So this is kind of the
space in which I think the interesting problems are.
I'm just gonna play it one second of the video just
Just You can see this on the web.
Meet Adrian, age six.
This is some great work. And his robot
friend, Kiwi. You are doing an
amazing job. This weekend morning,
they've settled in to play some games,
along with Big Brother Darren. Adrian
is on the autism spectrum.
And Kiwi is no toy.
It's a socially assistive robot.
You I will stop there.
It's on the web.
But here's a key thing. You can give kids a
screen and they will learn something, but they
will not learn everything. They may learn
about math, but they won't learn social skills. They
won't learn turn taking. They won't learn gaze.
They won't learn all the things.
They would learn a normal classroom, in a
normal social setting. And this is a thing we have to
scaffold because if we're creating society
in which people can't get along
with other people, this is problematic. So
we were historically doing a bunch of deep model
work on this because I'm telling you still foundation
models are terrible.
Dealing with data with really anomalous behavior.
Such as, you know, autism is very atypical.
Right? So general big models are gonna be terrible at
it. And we found that multi modality
was fundamental that looking at
small amounts of individual data and
then if you will now fine tuning with that, then doing
transfer learning, was way more
powerful. Than having a bunch of data
from a really high
variance population. Seems intuitive
in retrospect, but it's not what you do in ML.
If you have data from 50 people,
and you wanna predict this one person, you wanna
take all the 50 to predict to one,
No. Actually, you don't. You wanna take the data from
that one person that you have from three sessions
and value that way more than the other 50. So it's
a very counter intuitive machine
learning space of problems. I
always encourage people to think about because these conventional
problems may not scale.
So this idea of how much transfer to do from
an individual versus a larger
data set, Interesting problems.
I mentioned RL, just to tell you about RL.
Just even the problem of how does this
robot encourage the child to do the extra
but but it's not enough. Like, you'll have
to come, you have to manipulate
the level of challenge because
who knows. Right? I might be learning really fast, I
might get stuck. Or
in addition rather, you also have to manipulate
the feedback you give me. Because depending
on my personality for example, I might
require a lot of encouragement
because I come from an under resourced environment. I've
never been been good at anything and I just am used to
people telling me I'm stupid and so I I can't do this.
I can't do this. I can't do it. That's a very
typical behavior. Similarly, you have kids
who come from highly resourced environments
who have always told to been told that they're great,
they're getting a's, they're they're scared to
death of getting an a minus. Oh, my God.
I'm not gonna try that thing because I might not do
really well. Maybe some of you are
like that. So, you've got
problems on all sides. Because basically,
how do you motivate people to try really hard
things in order to learn? So this
RL has to be really complex. It's multiple
levels of RL that you're applying. It's
kind of interesting when you bring them together. How do you bring them
together? That's another hard problem.
I'm gonna just skip speech therapy. I will say
one other thing, big stuff in in dementia screening.
Everyone heard about dementia. Oh my god. What do we
do about dementia? It's a huge problem, societally.
Turns out, just from dialogue with the
elderly talking to a robot freely and
describing a picture, we were able
to do several things. We were first of all able to
engage elderly users with the robot. To
do a task that they would not do
with a doctor or with a family member.
So when you take an elderly person and you say describe
this picture for me, they don't wanna And so
the data that they give you is not
really representative of of their mental
state. Whereas with the robot, they
like to They played with it. And then they gave
us data they accepted the robot,
they they really enjoyed the robot way
better than humans. I'm talking
like humans in their family not not
random humans. And then we
actually showed and this was in
nature, that we could really highly
accurately predict early cognitive
decline. And the the heart of this
is that it was a natural conversation. It would
be even better if you tracked the data over time.
So diagnosis and screening for dementia is a
really big problem, but a lot of it has to do with
how do you get the person to actually behave in a
representative way? And so
these kinds of embodied interactions seem
to result in these outcomes.
I'll skip this. Most recent
work, we're putting these robots in dorms. This
is at USC. For
study companions with ADHD. Did you
know there's this concept of the body double? So,
if there's another body usually
a live human, in your
environment, it has to be a physical body
alive. In the environment.
Then you will focus better. And
if you have the ADHD, you will focus even better.
So, we thought well, can we put robots in there
and we found some really good outcome.
We're doing the same thing for anxiety and depression.
So now we're actually running an NIH clinical
trial. First one of its kind where we're
putting robots in many over a 120
dorm rooms And I just
wanna say very an interesting early result that
came already two years ago. We
compared chatbots to physical robots to notebook
methods, which is what you do for cognitive behavioral therapy.
And we found fundamentally that
students who were interact with
the robot were telling more personal
stories and they had more of what's called
alignment. So, when people
talk to models, we
talk differently to models than we talk to
physically embodied co present
entities. So, the best predictor
and believe me this is my last slide,
Second to last. The best predictor
of your outcomes when you go to therapy,
when you're doing therapy. You don't
have to go to therapy, it can be online. But the
best predictor of therapy outcomes
is how you align with your therapist.
So it doesn't matter whether you're whether you're doing cognitive
behavioral therapy, dialectical behavioral
therapy, breath work, Jungian, Freudian, doesn't matter.
That is not what matters. What matters
most is how well you get along
with and how productive your interaction is with
a therapist. That's called therapist
client alignment. Different notion of alignment.
The reason that that's important is because people
fundamentally talk to models differently and
chatbots for therapy are massive. They're everywhere.
But yet, how you engage with them, even though
you may feel much better after you talk
to them, and that's good. Doesn't
mean that they're having a therapeutic outcome.
So that alignment is not achieved and we did
some studies with validated measures
This is a NACCO paper and there's some other
papers following. To really show how
differently people behave based on what
we believe this thing
we're interacting with thinks it knows.
So you know when you're act reinteracting
with a model versus with a human.
And you behave differently? You may
think you don't, but you do.
And if you don't know, if I do a controlled experiment
and I tell you one thing, and it's
another, the data bear it out. Right?
Remember when we did one, we didn't tell them it was models, we told
them it was a human versus not?
People talk differently when they think it's a human.
So there's something about that humanity and embodiment
that makes a huge difference in health outcomes.
That's really important because that was the point of the story.
Right? Our our whole story was we
want to build this AI and robotics
that's personalized and adaptive
because most challenges are these long
term behavioral changes. And so I think
right now, we need to train
models with more of this engaged real time
interaction data. That's miss
in order to personalize interactions. And I also
think that a lot to be gained with smaller models
interacting with bigger models because right now, smaller
models are way better. And I
know people working on big models don't want to hear this,
don't wanna hear it. Nonetheless,
is what's happening. And it's not clear where the future is
for some really complex
like let's say autism data. When is it the
scale of those data ever going to match the scale
of the larger data set? Never. Should
it? So maybe there is something about
these small model large model interactions
that's an area that we need to also think
more about. Especially as you learn over time and
you're developing RL data.
Are in some sense a small model if you will.
I'll leave it there. I'm happy to, entertain
lots of debate on this. Anyway,
human centered human machine interaction
lots of You gotta
work with real data and you gotta get out of
whatever room you're in and into the real world.
Those are my two takeaways. Please
think about enhancing rather than replacing.
Everything. And that's
why we do what we do. And so I'm
just gonna say why do you do what you do?
Please think about it.
And thank you.
Thank you so much. We have time
for a couple of more questions maybe.
Yeah. Well, for
questions. The
how how do we do it with your questions? Okay. Yeah. There's
There's a mic.
Thank you, professor Mai.
Thank you for your wonderful speech. My name
is Di Dan. I was working
on official expression recognition back
in my PhD study,
but it was long time ago before
2022. So,
we have witnessed the, some
level of emotional intelligence appeared
in large language models,
but we don't seem to see
such breakthrough in
social emotional robots. So
my first question is, what do you think
is the major barrier that prevents
the success in tax
model to the social
emotion models. Social
emotion robots. And my second
question is, if we
can witness this breakthrough in the
future, what do you think is the most
promising pathway
via, per training or reinforcement
learning or an other
mechanism. That's all for my questions.
Thank you. Okay. So if I understand that
question correctly, you're saying that
you believe that the socio emotional
aspect has been solved with large models?
No. No. It hasn't. Right.
Right. So we agree that currently,
models are great at talking but they're not
really great at social and
emotional stuff. And in fact, I'll say that we've
done benchmarking with cognitive and
social behavior tests, like psychologically
grounded ones. And models are terrible at it. They
can be fine tuned. Right? So, I
don't think it's impossible, but I think it's a larger
training issue because if you just fine tune them,
with a little bit of data, you know,
they're it's gonna fall out of their head. Right? It's not
gonna be sustained. So we have to train, as
I keep saying, we have to train on richer
interactions that involve socio emotional
behavior. A whole lot more of that
So we will get there, but we'll only get there when
people understand that this is actually
really important for overall model
behavior. Right? And, I think we're not there. I think
people understand that we need cognitive
intelligence and physical intelligence,
they don't understand yet that we need social emotional
intelligence. But I also
worry a little bit about it too because once
we do, in a sense, get
there, then we're going to be even
better at manipulating people.
And that too is a risk. Does
that answer the question?
And my second question is that,
what would be the most promising past
way to the
cognitive behaviors of those models.
Oh, well, certainly, the answer
to that in some sense is easy, which is
we're not really looking at hard problems.
Right? So we're we're training models on
available dialogue data
which are too easy. Right? Like,
literally go into an elder care facility
and spend a day and think about
where would you insert AI there.
As opposed to sitting in your
office and thinking, oh, I'm gonna AI can
do this. Download a dataset. When you
go into an actual physical context in the
real world, you realize where the hard
problems are and how completely
far we are from meeting those. So I think it
pick any one of those data points. And that's
what you know, that's what I think that's
where our insights have come from. It's not that we're
so brilliant. It's that we go like, students
are motivated to go into a preschool. And
they look around and they see a bunch of bored students,
and then they're like, oh, what can I do to
engage these students with a robot? Oh, wow.
It's not easy. So,
real world people, real world.
Hi. Alex from Google.
So thank you so much for a very engaging talk.
So I guess in the a lot of us
in the industry are you know, living
the year of agents, and and I wanted
to get your perspective because all of
these agents are not embodied. Right?
I mean, some people are putting stickers on their mac
minis. They're they're showing that desire
do you see the evolution of these agents
from the perspective of how we could embody
them to help humans complete. And
achieve their task. Thank you for the question
about agents. I love that we're
now in the era of agents and it's
quote new. Because I literally have
a bag the agents conference from 1999.
So it's not new. AI, in
general, AI research has been working on agents forever,
but of course, the capabilities were so
much lesser than they are now. So I completely
agree. I think there is a there's there are
huge opportunities now because we can use models
to simulate behavior which is what agents are.
I think agents are still really limited in
that they're not doing what even older AI was
doing better, if I may say. Because
in the old days, we would say, wow, you know, we
have to keep history about the user.
We have to model the user and we have to represent
the user and models are still not doing
that. They're maybe having an attention window, but that's about
it. So some of that still has to be worked out.
Truly personalize to the user. Like my agent,
I wanted to know a lot about me and that's
starting the structures, the representations
for that are still being worked out. I
think we're gonna catch up Sometimes I think people
should read older papers, but they never do.
But I think it is really amazing though to
think about this world of all
of these deployed agents that are working on
our behalf. It's exciting, but I think
it's a little worrisome because to the extent
that every single agent has a slight
error in interpreting the original intent,
and then that scales out there. I think
someone ought to be modeling that stuff as well. I'm not sure if
that's happening. Anyway,
it's it's exciting times for sure, but it's
not new.
Thank you very much for the fantastic talk.
You mentioned in the talk that, very interesting
point, sometimes it's
way much better to train the model in a multi
model way. In a small
small sample size. Focus on
one particular case. And to
understand that deep instead of training
a 100 samples you know. Very
variety cases. Can you comment more on that?
And how do you think that can be done?
It specific?
Yeah. It's a it's a really hard problem.
Right? Because I think there a lot of
people who want to believe that models will eventually
get so big and so powerful that they will be
able to you know, just solve
any problem. Mean, if you
take the human brain as an example of that,
there's no reason to believe that because people who are
specialists are way, way, way better at the
thing that they do than the generalists. Right? And
we all talk about generalists are good at, like, you know,
an internist is someone who
can diagnose you then you need a specialist to really
know the details of what we should do. Now, we wanna
believe AI can do both, but we're yet to
come up with a mechanism that can actually do that because
the specialized data get diluted across the
whole thing just like they do in the
human brain. Right? So it's a it's a matter of attention
in the end. And so, that's why I
currently, in 2026,
I still think that there are a lot
of specialized models that we should leverage.
It's almost like having a bunch of specialized
models on top of a general model.
Because there is nothing better. It's general
models today are so
bad at these specific things.
And I'm not convinced
really right now. I mean, you ask me right now,
I'm not convinced that they ever will be that good. I think
if again, if we look at the model of human we
there is a reason why for
any finite model, any finite
brain, you do resource allocation. And,
if you really specialize like, you
know, literally like if I'm a violinist,
the part of my brain that deals with touching the
violin is bigger. There's a reason for
that. But you can't have it be bigger and
every other thing be bigger. Well,
some people in AI argue that you can,
then I think it's still a retrieval issue where you
can't so I don't
buy it right now, but I'm willing to be wrong.
I also think that's a longer path. So
if I want to solve real world problems,
the immediate solution is to work with smaller
models. Until we get to the bigger ones. I
don't wanna wait. I don't know how many years
to actually help people. Does that make
sense? Definitely. Thank you very
much. Alright.
Okay. Let let's thank the speaker.
She gonna be around. Yeah.
So Maya's gonna be here
Can feel free to ask her questions, and I think
the oral sessions
seven minutes. In
twenty minutes. Okay. So, we have a
little bit time. Awesome.